Mariano Riva Palacio Collection:
University of Texas at Austin
- Enero-Junio 1850
  - 4171 Villar, José del. Coyoacán, May 17, 1850. LS., 2 l. 22 × 27 cm.
    The Carmelitas affair discussed with the Padre Provincial; Carlos represented by Arizcorreta; Tlalpam; Tacubaya; situation in San Ángel; thanks for nomination to the tribunal; delay in pay. Includes note signed A. Noriega, on departure for Tlalpam; occurrence of cholera.
  - 4172 Terreros, Manuel. Mexico, May 18, 1850. LS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Request for interview to intercede on behalf of Lic. Franco, charged with irregularities by Fiscal Legorreta in trials before the Tribunal.
  - 4173 Sein, Antonio. Tula, May 18, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Instructions concerning the Alcalde de Tecozautla; report on cholera in Tula and Tepeji; vacancy in school staff; advertisement in Periódico oficial recommended; arrival of Noriega in Tlalnepantla with detachment of Seguridad Pública; Lagarde; collection of tax.
  - 4174 Lagarde y Gassin, Javier. Tula, May 18, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Shortage of weapons; delay in receipts from Colina; use of lances; Tlalpam detachment; funds needed for repair of weapons; need for swords and saddle equipment for protection of carbines; purchase of books; pay for soldiers.
  - 4175 Malo, José Ramón. Mexico, May 18, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Interview with MacKintosh, Baranda, and Bocanegra; appeal to Suprema Corte; interests in Guanajuato; celebrations at Tlalpam moved to Tacubaya; congratulations on elections to the Tribunal; praise of Toluca government from Morelia; Agustín [Cruz] in Tlalpam and San Agustín de las Cuevas; danger of postponement of Congress as result of cholera; arrival of English Packet; cholera in Havana.
  - 4176 Gómez Pedraza, Manuel. Mexico, May 18, 1850. LS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Support of Juez de Letras de T[l]a[l]nepantla Carlos Franco; unpleasant experiences in 1842 with Santa Anna, Gabriel Valencia, and Canalizo; suspension by the Tribunal Superior from the coveted position.
  - 4177 Sáenz de Sicilia, José I. Apam, May 18, 1850. LS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Appointment as Administrador de Apam; recommendation of Pedro Escudero y Echánove and Juan Núñez; explanation of slow collection of taxes.
  - 4178 Escudero P[edro]. Mexico, May 18, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Nominations for the Tribunal Superior; reforms in the aduana marítima and Dirección General de rentas; approach of the cholera; removal of family advised.
  - 4179 Martínez, Mariano. May 19, 1850. ALS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Arrest of Remigio Matías, Escudero, Juan Prada, and brothers of Lic. Barrera; arrest of los Cansecos.
  - 4180 Goribar, J. de. Casasano, May 19, 1850. ALS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Support in program of reducing state expenses; tax on estates; tax collection; tax on sugar and chinguirito; Pérez Palacios.
  - 4181 Madrid, Antonio. Mexico, May 19, 1850. ALS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Acknowledgement of appointment as Segundo Fiscal del Tribunal Superior; recommendation for Franquito.
  - 4182 Villaseñor, Alejandro. Cuernavaca, May 19, 1850. ALS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm., 1 l. 15 × 21 cm.
    Remedies for the cholera; medical reports; opposition to allowing novenas; memoria distributed by Almonte. Includes draft of answer, ordering detachment to Jonacatepec; Álvarez' help requested against conspirators in Tetecala; distribution of Almonte's Memoria.
  - 4183 Cueva, Ramón de la. Mexico, May 20, 1850. LS., 2 l. 21 × 28 cm.
    Epidemic in Mexico; sale of fruit prohibited; Padre Alcocer; examination of hacienda boundaries; collection from Señora Saldaña; tax payments; Agustín Cruz; request for appointment as notary.
  - 4184 Villamil, Gerónimo. Tezontlalpa, May 20, 1850. LS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Request for salary of $200 monthly to help his medical work among people suffering from the epidemic in Zumpango and Hueypoxtla; medical requirements; religious services.
  - 4185 De la Trouplinière, C. Cuernavaca, May 20, 1850. ALS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Survey of roads Toluca to Puente de Ixtla, Cuernavaca to Morelos, and Cuernavaca to Santiago Tianquistengo; guides furnished by José Juan Cervantes; Huichilaque; difficulties with the Alcalde de Palpa(?); report on estimated costs.
  - 4186 Villaseñor, Alejandro. Cuernavaca, May 20, 1850. LS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Fights over boundaries between Distrito de Matamoros and Distrito de Jonacatepec; funds needed for the Guardia Nacional; the Guardia detachment in Tepalcingo distrusted; reports from Cacahuamilpa of band forming at Mazatepec to attack Tetecala and free its prisoners; call for Oliveros; uprising at Chiautla; transmittal of letters from Morelos.
  - 4187 Sánchez Hidalgo, Manuel. Tulancingo, May 21, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Acknowledgement of nomination to the Tribunal Superior; El Siglo 19.
  - 4188 Villen (Villers?), Enrique Antonio. [Carta a José de Ágreda.] Solís, May 21, 1850. LS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Charges brought against Alcalde Ignacio Garduño by revoltosos in order to discredit the government; disagreement with Antonio Bejarano; efforts to stir up the Indians; trumped-up legal actions; Herrera; request for aid from the governor; good wheat harvest.
  - 4189 Torreblanca, Julián. Guerrero, May 21, 1850. LS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Request for back pay; arrangement in 1849 for pay in Taxco; request for pay in San Francisco Tetecala; transfer of funds to Juan Álvarez.
  - 4190 Villaseñor, Alejandro. Morelos, May 21, 1850. ALS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Plan to take troops to Jonacatepec; danger of Indian uprising; epidemic.
  - 4191 Otero, Mariano. Mexico, May 21, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Report on Senate: mix-up in elections, resignations, and substitutes among Pedraza, Otero, Herrera, Jáuregui, and Gamboa; resignation of Ibarra; Villar; influence of Manuel Robredo; Lacunza; need for new senator from the State of Mexico; opposition to law on bishoprics; approach of presidential elections; lack of interest in the election; inaction of the puros; support for Bravo and Arista; Almonte's self-promotion and support in Oaxaca, Yucatán, and Guerrero; Santanistas' seditious activity; plans to withdraw from public life; reduction of the army; lament over state of demoralization in the country; protest against prohibition of gambling in Tlalpam; Yáñez, Ortega, Cardoso in Tacubaya; entry of the epidemic in Mexico; death rate; charges against Franco in Tlalnepantla; substitution of Valle recommended.
  - 4192 Villar, José del. Coyoacán, May 22, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 22 × 27 cm.
    Gambling stopped in Tlalpam; quiet celebration with little business; letter of Pérez Fernández and petition of Joaquín Rosas and Gamio; celebration in Tacubaya; epidemic in Santa Anna de Milpa Alta; circulation of the Temis; articles suggesting his resignation.
  - 4193 Gómez, José F. Tixtla, May 22, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Need for an assay office; lawlessness of the area; assay office of Tomás Ávila in Taxco; Madariaga; delay in assembly of legislature; opposition to Cantú; departure of Diego; possible meeting with Bravo; copies of the Ley orgánica; Romero; lack of law enforcement; mines of Ajuchitlán; discovery of coal deposits; promise of business by ship with California; coal supplied California from England; collection of road tolls; division with the national government; road building; bridges over the Papagayo and Mexcala; contract in Acapulco for construction of a wharf; Álvarez' leave to visit his family and see to building of the forts and to inspect the mercury mine; discovery of mercury veins in Chilapa; epidemic.
  - 4194 Barrientos, José María. [Mexico,] May 22, 1850. LS. 1 l. 21 × 27 cm. Printed letterhead.
    Preventive measures against the cholera; Obra Pía de Lerma; Lic. Aguirre; Procession of Santa Teresa; question of banning public processions.
  - 4195 Flores, Ildefonso F[rancis] co. Zimapán, May 22, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Acceptance of appointment as Administrador de Rentas.
  - 4196 Andrade, Cristóbal. Zacualtipán, May 22, 1850. LS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Distribution of cholera medicine; collection of the contribución personal; uprising in Cahuazas reported by Ramón Mina.
  - 4197 Arista, Mariano. Mexico, May 22, 1850. LS. 1 l. 21 × 27 cm. Printed letterhead.
    Troops sent to Tlalpam; use of unemployed troops by Álvarez in road building suggested; road from Acapulco.
  - 4198 Villaseñor, Alejandro. Jonacatepec, May 22, 1850. LS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Withdrawal of insurgents from Jonacatepec; fear of Tepalcingo, Axochiapam, and Atlacahualoya, Indian towns; fear of further trouble; need for troops; distrust of Guardia Nacional; withdrawal of arms from Tepalcingo, detachment from Axochiapam led by Argüelles to Hacienda de San Ignacio on approach of rebels.
  - 4199 Malo, José Ramón. Mexico, May 22, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Interview with Mackintosh; Baranda; legal action in Estado de Querétaro; progress of epidemic; Dr. José María Varela killed; heavy rains; seditious incident in Tacubaya.
  - 4200 Terreros, Manuel. Mexico, May 24, 1850. LS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Protest of Indians of Tonanitla against the prohibition of fishing as a measure against the epidemic; dependence on fish; Romero.
  - 4201 Alcocer, Luis A. Tenan[]o, May 24, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Hacienda de Tepecingo; opposition and complaints against the government.
  - 4202 Aguirre, Manuel G. May 24, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Request for escort for Boneta; delivery of money to Ángel P. Palacios; the Memoria.
  - 4203 Iturbe, Francisco. Mexico, May 24, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Road construction in Tula; use of road tolls; road work stopped for period of the epidemic; gambling in Tacubaya.
  - 4204 COMPAÑÍA RESTAURADORA DEL MINERAL DE GUADALUPE, EN LA SIERRA MADRE SUR DE MORELIA. Mexico, May 25, 1850. Signed: Fernando Collado, Miguel J. Ussi, Secretario, and J. N. Almonte. 2 l. 21 × 27 cm., 1 l. 16 × 21 cm. Printed letterhead.
    Request for action on proposed expenses of the Mineral de Guadalupe, Coahuayutla, Estado de Guerrero; shares held by Riva Palacio; referral to José Mariano Larreátegui; death of Larreátegui in Morelia; meeting of shareholders in Portal de las Flores, Casa No. 1; cost of shares. Includes draft of answer, withdrawing from the transaction.
  - 4205 García, Juan M. Chalco, May 25, 1850. LS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Difficulties of Eduardo Burgos with the Administrador de contribuciones over tax for year spent in Juchi.
  - 4206 Arista, Mariano. Mexico, May 25, 1850. LS. 1 l. 21 × 27 cm. Printed letterhead.
    Troops send to Cuautla and Chiautla from Cuernavaca; plans of the anarquistas to start revolt in June.
  - 4207 Sánchez Solís, Felipe. I[nstituto] L[iterario], May 26, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Controversy with Campos over return of a chandelier.
  - 4208 Herrera y Campos, Francisco. Texcoco, May 27, 1850. LS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Progress of the epidemic; meeting of the Junta de caridad; Doloritas; money received from the Fuerza de Seguridad; receipts from Venta de Córdoba; medicine of sulfur and carbon.
  - 4209 Malo, José Ramón. Mexico, May 28, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Meeting with Mackintosh and Escudero; case placed before the Suprema Corte; involvement of States of Mexico and Querétaro; Guanajuato; progress of the cholera; illness of Agustín [Cruz.]
  - 4210 León, Esteban V. Zacualpan, May 28, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Uprising in San Andrés, Municipalidad de Tem[]c, led by Lieutenant Colonel Santos Barroeta and Luis Zamudio; absence of Calderón in Sultepec; fight with the Guardia Nacional; Santa Anna; troops sent by Juan León; pursuit of rebels by José Guerra; pay of the Fuerza de Seguridad Pública; return to Temascaltepec; irregularities in back pay.
  - 4211 Arrillaga, Basilio José. Mexico, May 28, 1850. LS., 2 l. 19 × 25 cm.
    Publication of the Recopilación of laws and decrees; Colección de Galván; request for subscription to new volumes. Primarily copy of letter of May 11.
  - 4212 Villar, José del. San Ángel, May 28, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 22 × 28 cm.
    Enforcement of gambling law; progress of the cholera; Coyoacán; Tomatlán; Dr. Santos Larrañaga working in Santa Anna; Aguirre; Valle; Antonio Martínez; Gamboa.
  - 4213 Villaseñor, Alejandro. Cuernavaca, May 29, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Need for pursuing the rebels and capturing their weapons; influence with Álvarez; pay needed for troops; lawlessness in Yautepec; progress of the cholera.
  - 4214 Sandoval, Joaquín. Tlalnepantla, May 31, 1850. LS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Progress of the cholera; medicines furnished from taxes; Monte Alto; Naucalpan; flight from the towns; Huisquiluca[n].
  - 4215 Importe de la paga del mes de mayo de 1850. Unsigned., 3 l. 21 × 31 cm.
    Table of payments. Notes in hand of Riva Palacio. Payments to Diputados, Gobernador, Teniente Gobernador, Secretarios, Archivo General, building expenses, Tribunal Superior, Tesorería general, Contaduría general, Instituto Literario; Penitenciaría; pensionistas Montepío, Juan Aranada, Ensayador, Seguridad Pública, Periódico oficial, Hospital de San Juan de Dios, León Guzmán, Felipe Antonio Arenas and Manuel Tinoco (Escribientes) Mariano Arizcorreta, Pedro Escudero y Echánove, Manuel Gracida, Pablo Martínez, Donaciano Mendoza, Antonio María, Mariano Castro, Rafael Escudero, Abogado de pobres Isidro Montiel, Marcos Calderón, Manuel Pasado, Juan Olmedo, Manuel Terreros, Joaquín Pérez Tejada, and Francisco Campero.
  - 4216 García, I. Cuernavaca, June 1, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Request for position in the Juzgado; support of Captain Mariano Gutiérrez; delivery of newspapers; Manuel [Gutiérrez].
  - 4217 Flores Pensado, Ignacio. Mexico, June 1, 1850. ALS., 1 l. 22 × 27 cm.
    Progress of the cholera.
  - 4218 Cruz, Agustín. Tenería, June 1, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Use of Raíz del indio for the cholera; the sulfur remedy; camphor used in Malinalco and Jalmolonga; remedies published in El Siglo; symptoms of the disease.
  - 4219 Sierra, Manuel María de la. Chalco, June 1, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Accusation against Primitivo Martínez by Juan Tolla for abuse of office.
  - 4220 Calderón, Lorenzo. Zacualpam, June 1, 1850. LS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Return from Sultepec; uprising in San Andrés; travel to Zacualpam; rebellious spirit toward the government; letter from Arista; Temascaltepec; precautions against rebellion; Texcaltitlán; need for powder and other equipment; tactics recommended.
  - 4221 Salonio, A. M. Jalapa, June 1, 1850. LS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Meeting of the Congreso General after end of the epidemic; Cueva.
  - 4222 León, Esteban V. Zacualpam, June 1, 1850. ALS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Temascaltepec; Calderón; Texcaltitlán; preparations against a June uprising; need for munitions.
  - 4223 Gavilán, Agustín P. Tetecala, June 1, 1850. ALS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Record of illness; unhealthy water claimed; Fiscal del Tribunal de Justicia; progress of the cholera; request for leave.
  - 4224 Andrade, José María. Mexico, June 1, 1850. ALS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Protest against prohibition on sale of fruits; Tlalpam; spead of cholera.
  - 4225 Sein, A[ntonio]. Tula, June 1, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Spread of cholera to Tepeji del Río; ingratitude of the Indians for relief measures; removal of Subprefecto de Zimapán; collusion with Juez de Letras; citizens of Jacala; Garrido.
  - 4226 Cumplido, Ignacio. Mexico, June 2, 1850. LS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Death of Otero; liquidation of accounts of Maneyro; Rodríguez; Barajas; subscriptions to scientific periodicals; arrival of periodicals in Veracruz for Colegio de San Gregorio; books of Manuel Recio; return of funds; cholera.
  - 4227 Martínez de Castro, C. Mexico, June 2, 1850. LS., 2 l. 22 × 25 cm.
    Recommendation for José María de la Peña; difficulties in collecting tax in El Mineral de Zimapán.
  - 4228 Téllez, Joaquín. Cuernavaca, June 2, 1850. LS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Complaint of Señora Alcocer; provisions for care of his illegitimate child.
  - 4229 Riva Palacio, M. [Borrador de carta a José María Andrade.] Toluca, June 3, 1850. Signed draft. 1 l. 21 × 27 cm. Printed letterhead.
    Complaint of citizens of Tlalpam.
  - 4230 Villaurrutia, Antero de. Mexico, June 3, 1850. LS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Use of Raíz del Indio as medicine against cholera; delivery by Escudero.
  - 4231 Barrera, Ignacio de la. Mexico, June 3, 1850. LS., 2 l. 17 × 22 cm.
    Return of son Vicente from the U. S.; lack of funds for the transportation; debt to Rosa; request for payment of back salary under new ruling of the Tribunal Superior; request for position for Vicente; knowledge of English and accounting.
  - 4232 Cruz, Agustín. Tenería, June 3, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Spread of the epidemic; Hacienda de Tepuxtepec; remedies.
  - 4233 Millán, Joaquín. Tenancingo, June 4, 1850. LS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Spread of the epidemic; use of Raíz del Indio; cases in San Simón, Tenería, Tepuxtepec, Chalma, Jalmolonga, Malinalco, and Temaloya(?).
  - 4234 Cruz, Agustín. Tenería, June 4, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Death of Otero; illness; spread of the cholera; remedies; Tepuxtepec.
  - 4235 Salvatierra, Miguel. Mexico, June 4, 1850. ALS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Bond posted for Miguel Salgado; imprisonment in La Acordada; inspection of mines and metal deposits in Guerrero; Álvarez.
  - 4236 Gómez, Nicolás. Hacienda del Moral, June 4, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Accounts prepared by Garrido; separation of Hacienda del Moral and Hacienda de San José; Asunción; Joaquinita.
  - 4237 Salgado, Miguel. Mexico, June 4, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Account of his arrest and imprisonment; Álvarez blamed for the arrest; letter to Alcalde de Puente de Ixtla; Juez de Buenavista; search for land titles in the Archivo General; Prefecto de Cuernavaca; bond by Miguel Salvatierra; travel with Lic. Gavilán; testing of mines; Almonte; land titles of San Antonio Buenavista; Miguel Arrioja, Director del Archivo General; mines in Teloloapam; Cerro del Gallo; Zacualpam; Almoloya; Sultepec; Tejupilco; Amatepec Panteoja (Cuadrilla o pueblito); Alahuistlán; Tlalchapa.
  - 4238 Paredes y Arrillaga, Agustín. Tulancingo, June 4, 1850. LS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Objection to use of local prison for criminals with long sentences; inadequacy of the prison facilities.
  - 4239 Martínez, José V(?). Tula, June 4, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Application for appointment as Juez propietario de Actopan; help of Martínez Basurto; Ixmiquilpan; Zimapán; Tula; Zacualtipán; recommendation for José María Jiménez; epidemic.
  - 4240 Terreros, Manuel. Mexico, June 4, 1850. ALS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Appointment of Pérez Tejada.
  - 4241 Cervantes, José J. Atenco, June 4, 1850. ALS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Request for supply of raíz del indio; Ana; Bernarda.
  - 4242 Lacunza, [José María]. Mexico, June 4, 1850. LS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Appointment as Fiscal of the Tribunal Superior; request for indefinite leave to attend to business in Mexico.
  - 4243 Cervantes, Darius (Marín?). [Carta a Francisco Iturbe.] Soyaniquilpan, June 5, 1850. LS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Construction of new road; complaint of high taxes.
  - 4244 Villaseñor, Alejandro. Cuernavaca, June 5, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Spread of the cholera; deaths in Tetecala and Miacatlán, and Mazatepec; Hacienda del Puente; remedies; Hacienda de San Gabriel.
  - 4245 León, Esteban V. Sultepec, June 5, 1850. LS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Provisions taken against a revolt; aid for Amatepec and Coatepec; armed troops in Temascaltepec; Seguridad Pública in Texcaltitlán; uprising in Cutzamala; Zacualpan.
  - 4246 Escudero, P[edro]. Mexico, June 5, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Receipt of supply of raíz del indio; Noriega; Ortega; Romero.
  - 4247 Martínez, Mariano. June 5, 1850. ALS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Illness; attention to duty.
  - 4248 Cuevas, Luis G. Mexico, June 5, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Recommendation for Antonio Canalizo; letter from Morelia; spread of cholera; death of Otero.
  - 4249 Montes y Otamendi, Luis Z. Actopan, June 5, 1850. ALS., 1 l. 22 × 27 cm.
    Appointment to replace Arrieta; recommendation for José Victoriano Martínez; Zimapán; Ixmiquilpan.
  - 4250 Haro y Tamariz, Antonio de. Mexico, June 5, 1850. LS., 2 l. 21 × 26 cm.
    Delivery of packet of raíz del Indio; distrust of local remedies; use of camphor, alkali, huaco, pepper and brandy, hot bricks; death of Otero; departure for Zacapoaxtla.
  - 4251 Noriega, A[gustín]. Mexico, June 5, 1850. ALS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Leave with one-third pay; Joaquín; Tlalnepantla; Junta de Sanidad in Tlalpam; difficulties with doctor.
  - 4252 Flores, Bernardo. Mexico, June 5, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Death of Mariano [Otero]; Rodríguez; the epidemic; Yáñez; Cumplido; progress of the illness; concern over the family of Otero; Andresita.
  - 4253 Morphy, Francisco. El Oro, June 5, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Notice of shipment of gold and silver to Mexico with Joaquín Pacheco; Queyimilpa(?); request for escort from Mexico until the return to Toluca or Lerma; avoidance of the cholera; route to San Rafael.
  - 4254 Colin, José Nicolás E. de. Asunción, June 5, 1850. LS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Barajas' furniture moved from Mexico; work at Tleconextlale, Cuigingo, Tejocote, Troje, Gabillero, and Chilar; barley crop in Nopalera; wheat in Santiago; transport of stones for the fence; masonry work; absence of the epidemic; receipt from Moral; Brother Luis; Cadena; Julián.
  - 4255 Malo, José Ramón. Mexico, June 5, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Interview with MacKintosh; Agustín [Cruz]; Tlalnepantla; deaths from epidemic.
  - 4256 Calderón, Lorenzo. Sultepec, June 5, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Disposition of troops in Temascaltepec and Texcaltitlán; local fears of an uprising; spread of the cholera in Coatepec and Amatepec; difficulty in collection of tax; León; notice of uprising in Cutzamala, State of Morelia; cholera in Tepepilco; Alas; Administrador de Zacualpam.
  - 4257 Riva Palacio, Mariano. [Borrador de carta a Cumplido.] Toluca, June 6, 1850., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Notice of death of Otero.
  - 4258 Villar, José del. San Ángel, June 6, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Provincial del Carmen; F. Carlos; Otero; spread of the epidemic; remedy; aceite del S. Vázquez de Sevilla; Valle's appointment; Olaguíbel's influence; El Río; Juzgado de Tlalpam.
  - 4259 Noriega, J[oaquín]. Mexico, June 6, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Illness of Agustín [Díaz]; absence from Tlalnepantla; Pedro Escudero; Otero; illness of Portu; spread of the cholera; comparison of remedies.
  - 4260 García, José María. Valle, June 6, 1850. LS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Improvement in the Guardia Nacional; new uniforms.
  - 4261 Granados de Medina, Francisco. Teloloapan, June 6, 1850. ALS., 1 l. 21 × 29 cm.
    Request for position as escribiente; service in Coyuca and Ajuchitlán.
  - 4262 Calderón, Lorenzo. Sultepec, June 7, 1850. LS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Epidemic in Tejupilco and Amatepec; decrease in talk of uprising.
  - 4263 Piña, Ramón. Santa María de Guadalupe Casipi, June 7, 1850. LS., 1 l. 21 × 25 cm.
    Difficulty in obtaining the raíz del indio; Juan García.
  - 4264 Iturbe, F[rancisco]. Mexico, June 7, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Complaint by citizens of Tlalpam; Marín Cervantes; Otero; spread of cholera; remedies; request for better handwriting. Includes draft of answer discussing road building in Tula; Tlalpam; Andrade; note on illness.
  - 4265 Esparza, Marcos de. Mexico, June 8, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Reluctance to accept new case; spread of the cholera; adjournment of legislature; Esparza and Pedraza on the Comisión de Gobernación; Otero; Ibarra's departure for Puebla, and Flores' to Lagos.
  - 4266 Jiménez, José María. Mexico, June 8, 1850. LS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.